<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Statsbylopez</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Statsbylopez</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>A state-space model to evaluate sports teams</title>
      <link>/post/a-state-space-model-to-evaluate-sports-teams/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/a-state-space-model-to-evaluate-sports-teams/</guid>
      <description>A few years ago at a statistics conference, Greg, Ben and I sat down to air a few greviences about our favorite sports. They were upset about baseball, and I was irked about hockey. Why the irritation?
Relative to other popular sports like basketball and football, it seemed to us at the time that the best team was winning less often in baseball and hockey. And as fans wanting skilled teams to be rewarded, it was frustrating to so often have well-constructed teams fall short of titles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On log-loss and scoring the NCAA tournament</title>
      <link>/post/on-log-loss-in-the-ncaa-tournament/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/on-log-loss-in-the-ncaa-tournament/</guid>
      <description>In 2014, Greg and I won the first annual Kaggle March Madness contest. This led to really cool things happening to a pair of nondescript statisticians that, to the likely detriment of our social lives, happened to know where to find good basketball data while also remembering, on a tight deadline, to enter type = &amp;quot;response&amp;quot; in our glm code.
The Kaggle victory was simultaneously awesome – like New York Times awesome – and embarassing, as Greg and I realized how lucky we were to have finished on top.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The impact of make-up calls is probably bigger than you think</title>
      <link>/post/the-impact-of-make-up-calls-is-probably-bigger-than-you-think/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-impact-of-make-up-calls-is-probably-bigger-than-you-think/</guid>
      <description>One of the more reliable indicators of which NHL team is likely to get the next power play has little to do with score or style of play. Instead, it&amp;rsquo;s been shown repeatedly (Ex 1, Ex 2) that referees call a substantially higher number of make-up penalties than would otherwise be expected in order to maintain an overall even number of violations on each team. Call it a biased impartiality &amp;ndash; in order to appear impartial by game&amp;rsquo;s end, ref&amp;rsquo;s let previous decisions drive future ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On the risks of categorizing a continuous variable (with an application to baseball data)</title>
      <link>/post/on-the-risks-of-categorizing-a-continuous-variable/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/on-the-risks-of-categorizing-a-continuous-variable/</guid>
      <description>To err is to human In the third inning during a contest a few weeks back between the Nationals and Cubs, Washington’s Brian Goodwin hit a line drive to left field with two outs and a runner on third. Despite an initial pause, Chicago’s Kyle Schwarber ran in and attempted to field the ball around his knees.
 Ruled an error on Schwarber, the play gave the a Nationals run in an eventual 9-4 win.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>