<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>NHL on Statsbylopez</title>
    <link>/tags/nhl/</link>
    <description>Recent content in NHL on Statsbylopez</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/nhl/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Lessons hidden in sports betting markets</title>
      <link>/post/lessons-hidden-in-sports-betting-markets/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/lessons-hidden-in-sports-betting-markets/</guid>
      <description>With sports betting now legal in several US states, I might as well give away my number one piece of advice for amatuers looking to gamble:
Don&amp;rsquo;t bet.
It&amp;rsquo;s an easy recommendation. Numbers implied by betting markets are too good, too close to the truth that, when accounting for the vig, it&amp;rsquo;s nearly impossible to make a long term profit.
But just because your local statistician tells you not to bet doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t check out betting market odds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Part I: Randomness of regular season competition</title>
      <link>/post/part-i-randomness-of-regular-season-competition/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/part-i-randomness-of-regular-season-competition/</guid>
      <description>One of the most humbling aspects of being a sports fan is that the better team doesn&amp;rsquo;t always win.
It could happen for a few reasons. The better team might get unlucky, whether it&amp;rsquo;s a missed foul call or bad bounce. The better team might play poorly, missing open three-pointers, field goals, or easy saves. Or the &amp;ldquo;better&amp;rdquo;&amp;rdquo; team might simply be so close in terms of talent to the &amp;ldquo;worse&amp;rdquo; team that any number of plays, shots, or referee decisions could play into the game&amp;rsquo;s outcome, actions that, by and large, are largely noise and not indicative of any particular skill or talent.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Vegas flu looks real — but somehow the Chicago Blackhawks also got sick</title>
      <link>/post/the-vegas-flu-looks-real/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-vegas-flu-looks-real/</guid>
      <description>In yesterday’s post, I walked through the use of a state-space model to evaluate NHL team strength over the course of an NHL season.
But analyzing team strength is just the start of how we can use this type of framework to analyze betting market data in sports. In today’s post, I’ll ask a different question – What team had the best home advantage? And did perceptions of any teams (cough cough, Vegas) change over the course of the season?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A state-space model to evaluate sports teams</title>
      <link>/post/a-state-space-model-to-evaluate-sports-teams/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/a-state-space-model-to-evaluate-sports-teams/</guid>
      <description>A few years ago at a statistics conference, Greg, Ben and I sat down to air a few greviences about our favorite sports. They were upset about baseball, and I was irked about hockey. Why the irritation?
Relative to other popular sports like basketball and football, it seemed to us at the time that the best team was winning less often in baseball and hockey. And as fans wanting skilled teams to be rewarded, it was frustrating to so often have well-constructed teams fall short of titles.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The impact of make-up calls is probably bigger than you think</title>
      <link>/post/the-impact-of-make-up-calls-is-probably-bigger-than-you-think/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/the-impact-of-make-up-calls-is-probably-bigger-than-you-think/</guid>
      <description>One of the more reliable indicators of which NHL team is likely to get the next power play has little to do with score or style of play. Instead, it&amp;rsquo;s been shown repeatedly (Ex 1, Ex 2) that referees call a substantially higher number of make-up penalties than would otherwise be expected in order to maintain an overall even number of violations on each team. Call it a biased impartiality &amp;ndash; in order to appear impartial by game&amp;rsquo;s end, ref&amp;rsquo;s let previous decisions drive future ones.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>